Guide to the Abraham G. Mills papers, 1793-1929 [bulk 1863-1929]
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Abraham G. Mills papers
1793-1929
1863-1929
2006
MssCol 2006
Mills, Abraham Gilbert, 1844-1929
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
8.8 linear feet (11 boxes, 1 package)
Abraham Gilbert Mills (1844-1929) was a New Yorker who worked as Chief Clerk for the Supervising Architect of the U.S. Treasury Dept. and then entered the elevator business where he became a vice-president of the Otis Elevator Company. Mills, who was interested in amateur and professional sports, served as president of the National League of Professional Baseball Clubs from 1882 to 1884, was a supporter of the American Olympic movement, and was a member and officer of the New York Athletic Club. Having served in the Civil War, he became active in veterans organizations, particularly the Grand Army of the Republic. Collection consists of correspondence, diaries, artifacts, and printed matter documenting most aspects of Mills's life. Bulk of collection is personal and business correspondence, 1874-1929. There are two diaries, 1871-1872 and 1885, as well as letters, documents and clippings relating to the N.Y. Athletic Club, the Otis Elevator Co., baseball, the Adirondack League Club, and the Grand Army of the Republic. Also, news clippings, visual materials, artifacts, certificates, and printed ephemera.
Abraham G. Mills (1844-1929) was a New Yorker who worked as Chief Clerk for the Supervising Architect of the U. S. Treasury department and then entered the elevator business where he became a vice-president of the Otis Elevator Company. Mills, who was interested in amateur and professional sports, served President of the National Base Ball-League (1882-1884), was a supporter of the American Olympic movement, and was a member and officer of the New York Athletic Club. Having served in the Civil War, he became active in veteran's organizations, particularly the Grant Army of the Republic.
The papers document most aspects of Mills' life. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence (including four letters from Samuel L. Clemens) and 62 volumes of letterbooks containing personal and business letters (1874-1911) There are two diaries (1871-8372, 1885) as well as letters, documents, and clippings relating to the N. Y. Athletic Club, the Otis Elevator Co., baseball, the Adirondack League Club, and the Grand Army of the Republic. News Clippings, visual materials, artifacts, certificates, and printed ephemera comprise the rest of the collection.
1933-1935, Received from Mary Mills Lyall
Mills, Abraham Gilbert, 1844-1929; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Adirondack League Club; Grand Army of the Republic; National League of Professional Baseball Clubs; New York Athletic Club; Otis Elevator Company; United States. Department of the Treasury; United States. Dept. of the Treasury; Athletics -- United States; Baseball -- History; Elevator industry -- United States; Sports -- United States; Veterans -- Societies and clubs; Diaries; Photographs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Businessmen
- Abraham G. Mills writings (Box 1)
- Abraham G. Mills diaries, [1871-1872]; [1885] (Box 1)
- Correspondence -unsorted, circa 1865-1929]; 8 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence-S. L. Clemens, [1839] (Box 1)
- Otis Elevator Company, [1888-1929] (Box 1)
- New York Athletic Club, [1888-1929] (Box 1)
- Baseball, 1879-1927 (Box 1)
- Adirondack League Club, [1895-1906] (Box 1)
- Grand Army of the Republic (Box 1)
- Abraham G. Mills personal papers — unsorted, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Organizations and clubs (Box 2)
- News clippings and articles (Box 2)
- Printed ephemera (Box 2)
- Visual materials (Box 3)
- Badges, medals, and 1 plaques (Box 4)
- Certificates, [1793-1863]; in brown package (Box 5)
- Personal and business letterbooks, [1874-1887]; 4 volumes (Box 6)
- Business letterbooks, [1890-1905]; 7 volumes (Box 6)
- Personal letterbooks, [1887-1890]; 2 volumes (Box 6)
- Personal letterbooks, [189?-1890]; 11 volumes (Box 7)
- Personal letterbooks, [1899-1903]; 13 volumes (Box 8)
- Personal letterbooks, [1899-1903]; 11 volumes (Box 9)
- Personal letterbooks, [1903-1906]; 10 volumes (Box 10)
- Personal letterbooks, [1906-1908]; 3 volumes (Box 11)
- Personal letterbooks, [1908-1911]; 2 volumes (Box 12)